so I have a question for m a friend he
wants to know bante how could Arun and
Mala transform from a mass murderer to
an could
angul can someone grasp the dummer
deeply despite such a dark
past was there no guilt or shame for his
deeds so
well yes technically
uh somebody can grasp the dhama despite
such like severe
actions like like what G angulimala did
but obviously those are you know would
be far and few even back in the Buddhist
time when it was the most optimal time
for the practice of the dhama he was
like one in a
million far more people there many more
murderers and people that committed
crimes that that because of that it
would prevent them from understanding
the dhama like the King who uh who
killed his father the previous
King uh when he went to listen to the
Buddha and the Buddha kind of uh taught
him the D and everything and he was
rejoicing and he was like very inspired
but he did not become a sod and when he
left the Buddha said oh it's because he
killed his father if he didn't kill his
father he would have got a Right View
right here right now upon listening to
me but he didn't because of that so but
now you might see oh there's some
magical connection between oh he
committed murder thus it prevents him
from the dam no it's actually the reason
that prevented him from understanding
the dhama there and then when the Buddha
was teaching him face to face was also
present there and then that reason
because of which he did not become a
s and the reason being yes he killed the
father but see angulimala killed many
people but then he was able to turn it
around so what's the difference between
the two well the difference is uh
contrary to lack of Shame and lack of
remorse for what he did angul Mala was
actually able to take the weight of all
of his
actions transparently authentically and
feel the the full extent of what he
did which most people would probably go
mad if they were to accept it like
everybody you know who who basically who
commits such heinous acts has to have
some sort of excuse some sort of cover
up some sort of kind of uh bluring of
responsibility has to cannot take it
upon himself no I did this and fully
experienced the the the the the entire
extent of that action and that's why
that King who killed his father did not
become a San he could not admit to
himself he could not
accept fully what he did the the weight
because he would have crushed him the
remorse would have crushed him I mean
his own father who raised him and
everything so I'm sure he instead of he
came probably close to accepting it upon
listening to the Buddha but chose to you
know Double Down um towards his
reasoning towards his justifications for
whatever reasons he would have done such
a thing uh well angula didn't do that
when he met the Buddha when the Buddha
gave him the short teaching it sort of
cut through all of it and he was
actually able to accept and that's why
he was able to become an Arun it's that
like very drastic non-compromising
authenticity of taking responsibility for what you
of taking responsibility for what you
did what you've been doing how you've
been acting and infinitely taking that
responsibility not like oh until
tomorrow and then tomorrow I'll become
an arand or something no no no you don't
know how long it will take you don't
even know you're going to succeed that's
secondary first and foremost is you got
to accept what you
did and basically learn to live with it
so to speak without covering up without
I was because of this or I was in this
state or that said no whatever that
might have been those extending
circumstances still I did those things
cuz I consciously chose to do them and
that is a prerequisite for understanding
the dhama and that's exactly the
difference why somebody like anguli Mala
who committed so many murders and and
and who knows what else was actually
able to become an
Arun and then some people who didn't
even commit a murder but were kind of
immoral in some smaller ways that
prevented them from becoming even
aaan because they were not they were not
admitting it to themselves they were not
really allowing the weight of diretion
to sink in and you can see that in in
mundane examples day-to-day life um
generally people avoid anything that
would produce a sense of shame in them
guilt or
remorse now they don't necessarily avoid
it beforehand before they do it but they
tend to avoid taking responsibility
after they've done such things through
carelessness so you act carelessly you
break the precepts you misbehave and so
on and then afterwards you sort of have
when you stop you have an option to now
accept and feel bad for what you did and
endure it for as long as it takes until
the mind kind of grows out of it or you
kind of turn a blind eye and then double
down and continue doing more to just
keep you keep yourself in that Perpetual
state of motion so you you don't have to
stop and think about it what you
did and that's if if that attitude is
not abandoned if that's not changed
there is absolutely no any no basis for
any practice of the dhama whatsoever
doesn't matter how many sutas you read
how strictly you have to first admit
accept uh the weight of uh of unh
wholesome and uh if possible even like
confess it confess your shortcoming your
your your trans transgressions like the
S would
say so any coverups coverups basically
internal coverups like you have to bring
them out to light you don't have to I
don't mean like you have to go publicly
now and declaring to everyone what you
did but you have to do it to yourself
and you also have to do it in a sense
that if it were to be brought up you
will not cover it up you will say how it
is there was that another example of a
monk on his death bed being ill and kind
of and and other monks as The Bu to go
and see him because apparently he wasn't
he didn't even have the right View and
he's about to die so the Buddha goes and
asks him and he says yeah like you know
he still didn't understand the teaching
he's not a Sana and um and that's uh and
basically he was like um you know he was
sort of
remorseful and and and and a bit you
know mental anguish and the Buddha say
why are you why are you remorseful
because you didn't you did not become a
sopan is it because you know you did
things by Body spiritual mind that you
have not confessed that you have not
brought to light that you have not made
transparent he says no no no no no I've
been I've been pure I've been behaving
well it's just that I still haven't
understood the DH that's the sole reason
for my remorse and then the would taught
him the D and he became a s before he
died he understood it but that is a
factor that that is a factor that that
kind of drastic uh acceptance of
of drastic uh acceptance of
responsibility as we often talked about
I mean we had many talks about the role
of responsibility and freedom from
suffering and so
on there's a second part of this
question he says I wonder why despite
not committing such actions and
earnestly seeking dhama I still struggle
to reach Aran there you go that's the
answer um you have to you have to and
like if he like well I haven't done
anything bad it's relative you know for
a small mind even minor little kind of
infractions and actions can be more than
enough to pollute it like the Buddha
gave that example you know you put a you
put a like I don't know a drop of d D
into a
glass it's going to dye the whole amount
of water but then you put a drop of dye
in an ocean is not going to make a
difference so you don't know how
developed your mind is but the fact is
if you're not getting the right view if
you're not progressing in the Dharma
keeping the precepts means okay so you
need to you need to dig deeper
basically you need to um be more more
serious with your sense restraint more
serious with avoiding
distractions more serious with kind of
giving into these little um ways out of
of enduring the the the pressure of
withdrawal of saying no to sensuality
and then see what comes up what's going
to kind of what that pressure will bring
something to the
surface and then see what what mind
starts revolving around what are you
remorseful and not in a sense I have to
go and deal with this before I can start
practicing no no you're dealing with
this by bringing it up you're dealing
with it by not covering it
up and quite contrary to the popular
expectation you're not actually trying
to resolve
it you're trying to train your mind so
it stops resisting it while it's there
so you don't want to resolve it in that
sense when you bring these things up um
again as I said you know if it's like
major breaches of precepts that needs to
be confessed that needs to be um refer
to somebody else as well just just you
make it public in that sense it makes a
different to your state of mind but now
we're talking about you know somebody
didn't do anything bad necessarily
hasn't harmed anybody hasn't didn't
steal anything nothing like that but
still not progressing in the
DH so you need to start digging in
further within yourself in that sense of
sense restraint that will bring up
various you know well neurotic
Tendencies to put it that way your mind
might resist that it was it was start to
push you to to to make you act out
toward sensuality or real will and so on
then you're going to start feeling
guilty on the kind of things that kind
of irrational and you have to go through
that it's basically like a like a mind
that has been caught or that has been
sort of
Trapped uh it's going to start to kick
and scream and resist initially and and
throw everything it has at
you until it comes down so that's the
point you're bringing all of that up so
to teach teach your mind how to calm
down within these things that are
assailing you not to calm down by
resolving them and making them go away
no because if you were calm while
they're there that's how they go
away if mind is calm down within those
things within that pressure of
responsibility within the neurotic kind
of uh Tendencies within everything else
like that that like your thoughts
wanting to make you act toward
sensuality your mind does not act
endures it count down again the bud
described it so many times like an
elephant in the battle that's being
prodded by Spears with whips whatever
Thunder and it doesn't Flinch that's how
you need to train your mind that's
exactly what it is that's definition of
Samar so angulimala obviously did that
despite the weight of his actions the
weight of his remorse the weight of his
regret the consequences of everything he
did everything was reminding him of what
he did I mean people were beating him up
on the street throwing stones at him
even later
years but he endured it all and the B
actually told him bear
it bear it that's that's that's
basically that's that's the extent of
your punishment that's it you're not
going to have more because you have
freed your mind to fully accepting
responsibility for that that then enable
you to understand the Dharma and the
actual roote of suffering and the way
out of
suffering so the point is to train your
mind within the container of of these
unpleasant emotions weight of responsibility and so
emotions weight of responsibility and so
on train it in the sense of learn how to
keep it calm without trying to get rid
of what's sort of bothering you in know
you know so I'm good Mala whatever
happened in his life whatever pressure
arose for him made him so angry so
violent was killing people he was doing
a lot of stuff yeah and so the only way
to to uproot that those Tendencies of
violence and anger and so on you would
have to face that pressure which he
which he's been running away his whole
life that made him do such bad actions
now not just that he had to accept that
pressure he now had to accept the whole
amount of the bad actions that he did on
account of that pressure and he did and
so that the tendency to lash out
violently he did yeah he has to bear
that he has to bear that
habit yeah a serious habit like habit
that had serious consequences exactly so
and that's my point see it doesn't
matter whether it was something as as
severe as angul mala's case or some
minor things you're doing but the
principle Remains the Same are you
acting out are you distracting yourself
are you covering up are you not enduring
things on the right level and by that I
mean see you have an unpleasant emotion
present itself on account of something
you did or something you said or
somebody else did or somebody else said
are you trying to get rid of it are you
trying to psychologize it explain it no
that's already acting out that's learn
how to remain unmoved by it and when you
succeed well then you won't care whether
it's coming or going that thing that's
pressuring you whether it's present or
it's not present because either way
you're not
moving without needing to to do anything
on account of it without needing to act
out without needing to to meditate and
concentrate away and N none of that's
necessary then CU all of that was done
because you were moved in the first
place so he he learned how to no longer
crave or resist against pain pretty much
he freed himself from that fundamental
paa fundamental resistance yeah towards
his own form towards his own state of
being so and that's I think his name was
then he was then called on violence the
nonviolent one cuz he was well again he
had to so drastically develop the the
attitude of nonviolence because of his
violent attitude before that that became
his defining
characteristic but but that's the thing
so even
though why I'm not a killer I don't
murder people so on but I I get annoyed
at mosquitos yeah there's that that root
of murder resistance the root that
resistance I get annoyed mosquitos or it
um sounds sounds are bothering me but
some what he's like saying or what I'm
hearing he's just bothering me as a as a
as a neutral sound uh boredom as well
again like I fear it I need I need
something to do I need something to keep
me occupied I can't accept my state of
being for what it is I resist
it I resist it I become cranky when I'm
cranky I lash out when I lash out I
basically um publicly sort of uh perform
actions that are unsuitable then I'm
ashamed then I cover up the shame then I
justify it then I say it's because of
this or that then I continue but
continue perpetuating the same principle
so when next time it happen same you you
go through the same motion same cycle
like you have to accept it and even if
it's not your fault as I often
say initially you have to accept
responsibility even for that because
your whole life up to that point was
about avoidance of responsibility so now
you have to accept responsibility for
random circumstances and things that
might happen to you that you you
generally didn't act out but you will
have to accept responsibility until it
sinks in in your mind that okay no
this acceptance of responsibility should
not be moving me should not be
pressuring me should not be uh making me
resist it and act out and trying to
outrun it the only reason it does so is
because well because of the UNH
wholesome habit of avoiding it through
sensuality acting out of ill will and distraction